Guide to the John H. Shober Sr. papers 1832-1952
Montana Historical Society
John H. Shober Sr. papers
1832-1952
Montana Historical Society> Archives
MC 69
Shober, John H., 1832-1925
2.5 linear feet of shelf space
John Shober (1832-1925) was a Helena, Montana, miner, attorney, and state legislator. Collection (1832-1952) includes descriptions of frontier social and mining conditions. Included are subgroups for Shober's nephew John H. Shober, Jr., manager of a ranch near Townsend; and of his niece Harriet Shober Nolan, wife of Cornelius B. Nolan.
John Shober was born in Loudon County, Virginia, on January 5, 1832. After attending law school in Cincinnati, Shober was admitted to the Ohio bar in 1852. In 1854 he began practicing law in Minnesota where he participated in the organization of Dodge County. In 1858 Shober moved to Yankton, Dakota Territory. While in Yankton he was elected to the Territorial Council, serving as its president in 1862. Shober participated in the initial formation of the Dakota Territory after his election to the Territorial Council. He served as the Council's president in 1862.
In 1864 Shober joined the Sully Expedition and travelled to Montana Territory, arriving in Helena by September, 1864. He mined in Nelson and Holmes Gulches, while beginning his law practice in Helena. In 1865 he ran for district attorney and defeated Cornelius Hedges. He won that office again in 1867. That year Shober also formed a law partnership with Thomas J. Lowry. Shober, an ardent Democrat with pro-Confederate sympathies during the Civil War, was elected a member of the 1866 Constitutional Convention. In 1894 Shober was elected to the Fourth Legislative Assembly as a Populist.
Shober invested in mining and ranching properties. The Elkhorn Mining Company (established in 1883) and the Montana Mining and Improvement Company (established in 1887) were two of his larger investments. Shober was a pioneer in the formulation of mining and water rights law. John H. Shober never married and was cared for in his old age by his niece Harriet Shober Nolan. Shober died in Helena on August 22, 1925.
John H. Shober, Jr. was born in Dexter, Iowa, about 1870. He was the son of Nerva and Herod Shober and the nephew of John H. Shober. He worked on his father's farm, attended Rathbun's Business College in Omaha, Nebraska (1888-1890), and entered the feed business with his father in Dexter in 1891.
In 1900 Shober left Iowa and settled on his uncle John Shober's ranch near Townsend, Montana. He continued to manage his uncle's property for a number of years, and after the death of his uncle and his sister Harriet Shober Nolan (1929), he moved to Helena where he entered the real estate business. John H. Shober never married. He died in 1952.
Harriet Shober was born in Dodge County, Minnesota, in the early 1850s and moved to Dexter, Iowa, when she was sixteen years old. The teaching certificates she earned between 1876 and 1885 enabled her to teach in the Adair County, Iowa, schools.
In 1887 Harriet moved to Helena, Montana Territory, and lived with her uncle John H. Shober. In 1894 she married Cornelius B. Nolan, a Helena attorney, and involved herself in Helena's social affairs. Harriet Nolan, like her uncle, was active in Democratic politics and served as Democratic National Committeewoman for several years.
Harriet Shober Nolan died at Lake McDonald, Montana, on August 23, 1929.
This collection consists of three subgroups: John H. Shober; John H. Shober, Jr.; and Harriet Shober Nolan.
The John H. Shober subgroup contains interview notes with Shober by A.J. Noyes (circa 1917), miscellaneous incoming correspondence, outgoing correspondence, financial records, legal documents, and miscellany. The majority of the correspondence is between John and his father George and brother Herod. John H. Shober describes the conditions in Dakota and Montana in the early and mid-1860s. Several letters describe the mining conditions in and around Helena. Other correspondence reflects John Shober's political attitudes in the 1860s and 1870s. The financial and legal records in this subgroup document Shober's mining investments. There are also some miscellaneous materials including some memo books belonging to George Shober, some identification papers, etc.
The John H. Shober, Jr. subgroup consists of incoming correspondence (primarily love letters) (1880s-1940s) and some miscellaneous general correspondence. The legal documents and the three subject files in this subgroup deal with his interest in several mining companies. There are also some miscellaneous items.
The Harriet Shober Nolan subgroup consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence (1877-1929), including letters from suitors and from Cornelius B. Nolan prior to his marriage to Harriet, as well as correspondence from school friends who became teachers and administrators at the Northern Indiana Normal School and Business Institute in Valparaiso, Indiana. The subgroup also contains some minor financial records (1928-1929) and miscellany (1876-1926).
Arranged by subgroup and series. Some material housed in oversize folder in archives map case. See inventory below for more information.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
Printed material, maps, photographs, and artifacts transferred to Library, Library Map Collection, Photograph Archives, and Museum respectively. See inventory below for more information.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Shober, John H., 1832-1925; Nolan, Harriet Shober, -1929; Shober, John H. 1870-1952; Nolan, Cornelius B., 1855-1922
Helena (Mont.)--Commerce; Helena (Mont.)--Description; Helena (Mont.)--Politics and government; Helena (Mont.)--Social life and customs; Lewis and Clark County (Mont.)--Politics and government; Yellowstone National Park--Description and travel; Yellowstone National Park--Leased departments, concessions, etc.; Townsend (Mont.)
Frontier and pioneer life--Montana; Mines and mineral resources--Montana--Jefferson County; Mines and mineral resources--Montana--Lewis and Clark County; Mines and mineral resources--Montana--Silver Bow County; Overland journeys to Montana; Political parties--Montana; Railroad travel; Ranches--Montana; Legislators--Montana; Broadwater County (Mont.)--Agriculture
Montana; Ranching; Mines and Mineral Resources; Women
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- John H. Shober, Sr.
  - Biographical Materials
    - Interview notes by A.J. Noyes, circa 1917 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - B-W (correspondents include Mary A. Baughman, William Caskey, James M. Cavanaugh, John M. Cotter, George B. Edgerton, G. S. Foos, Patrick Howard, J. B. Hubbell, R. M. Johnson, A. W. Puett, Klingel and Quam, Dac [?] Wallace), 1838-1893 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - Harriet Shober Nolan, 1877-1890 (Box-folder 1 / 3-5)
    - George Shober, 1858-1869 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
    - Herod Shober, 1862-1886 (Box-folder 1 / 7-8)
    - Miscellaneous family correspondence, 1866, 1921 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Financial Records
    - Certificates of mining claims filed, etc., 1854, 1863-1865 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
    - Journal of court costs and fees, 1877-1889 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Legal Documents
    - Agreements; certificates; powers of attorney, 1863-1894 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
    - Deeds; mining claims, 1868-1894 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Printed Materials
    - Books belonging to Herod Shober (includes A Key to the western calculator and The Schoolmaster's calculator), 1815, 1831 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
    - List of printed materials transferred to library (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Miscellany
    - Memo books belonging to George Shober, 1858-1866 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
    - Identification papers, invitations, etc., 1827-1912 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
- John H. Shober, Jr.
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - Cornelia Arndt, 1909-1911 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
    - Marion McNaughton Bacon, 1900-1911 (Box-folder 2 / 2-3)
    - Myrtle Coyle, 1896-1900 (Box-folder 2 / 4-6)
    - Myrtle Coyle, 1900-1902 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
    - Henrietta Wine DeWalt, 1900, 1930-1933 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
    - Florence Foster, 1903-1909 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
    - Harriet Marks Loble, 1929-1945 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
    - Ella Lyon, 1888-1893 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
    - Cornelius B. Nolan, 1900-1922 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
    - Harriet Shober Nolan, 1886-1926 (Box-folder 3 / 7-8)
    - Mary Elizabeth Salmon, 1905-1911 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
    - Laura Sherlock, 1901 (Box-folder 4 / 2)
    - Helen L. Smith, 1905 (Box-folder 4 / 3-4)
    - C-Z (correspondents include Herbert Constable, Matie Cook, P. M. Donar, M. L. Edwards, W. E. Gaston, George W. Fisk, Gertrude Foresman, Lizzie A. Johnston, Idah Kinnear, E. G. Paul, Madison D. Yonell, unidentified), 1887-1899 (Box-folder 4 / 5)
    - B-W (correspondents include Alfred F. Bissell, Butler and Alger, Mrs. R. Carlston, Lillian A. Cox, Art Eastman, Hinkson and Brown, Eva M. Kerr, Geroge Allen McCorkle, George Robertson, Fred S. Rowe, Mary Shober, Beatrice Shaffer, George W. Winter, unidentified), 1900-1901 (Box-folder 4 / 6)
    - A-W (correspondents include G. L. Atwater, Alice B. Cole, Josie Cunningham, Clara Leib, Allie R. Morrison, Lena Williams, unidentified), 1902-1906 (Box-folder 4 / 7)
    - B-T (correspondents include Alice B. Cole, Josie Cunningham, J. A. Everitt, Alice J. Minckler, Sadie T., unidentified), 1907-1910 (Box-folder 4 / 8)
    - C-T (correspondents include Sue Cummings, B. N. Donar, Carl Herter, Thomas M. Hodgens, Lang Bros., Alice and Fred Markham, Muriel Mayer, Mary Shober, Sadie T., unidentified), 1911-1920 (Box-folder 4 / 9)
    - C-U (correspondents include Sue Cummings, Hecla Mining Company, D. V. Higbie, Cornelius B. Nolan, Muriel Mayer, Mae M. Rasch, George F. Stewart, United States General Land Office), 1921-1945 (Box-folder 4 / 10)
    - Family and miscellaneous (correspondents mostly unidentified), undated (Box-folder 5 / 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence
    - Outgoing, plus non-Shober letters, 1881-1915 (Box-folder 5 / 2)
  - Court Papers
    - J.H. Shober, Jr. vs. William M. Blackford as administrator of the Estate of Philip I. Moule bills of exception, 1907 (Box-folder 5 / 3)
  - Financial Records
    - Receipts, statements, miscellaneous, 1891-1922 (Box-folder 5 / 4)
  - Legal Documents
    - Deeds, agreements, 1872-1931 (Box-folder 5 / 5)
  - Maps
    - Plat of T5N, R2E showing land lost to Northern Pacific Railroad [near Toston], undated (Box-folder 5 / 6)
    - List of plats transferred to Library Map Collection (Box-folder 5 / 7)
  - Photographs
    - List of photographs transferred to Photo Archives (Box-folder 5 / 8)
  - Printed Material
    - List of printed material transferred to the Library (Box-folder 5 / 9)
  - Subject Files
    - Apex Mine, 1891-1946 (Box-folder 5 / 10)
    - Boulder Chief Mine, 1887, undated (Box-folder 5 / 11)
    - Boulder Chief Mine [Map Case-See MC 65-71 Folder], 1887, undated (Oversize-folder MC 65-71)
    - Townsend Ranch and Canal, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 5 / 12)
    - Townsend Ranchy and Canal [Map Case-See MC 65-71 Folder], 1939-1940 (Oversize-folder MC 65-71)
    - Virginia Consolidated Mining Company, 1913-1952 (Box-folder 5 / 13)
    - Virginia Consolidated Mining Company [Map Case-See MC 65-71 Folder], 1913-1952 (Oversize-folder MC 65-71)
  - Miscellany
    - Invitations, 1900-1913, undated (Box-folder 5 / 14)
    - Membership in Montana Loyalty League; invitations to Lambs Club, Informal Club and Shirtwaist Dancing Club), 1901-1911, undated (Box-folder 5 / 15)
    - Poems, undated (Box-folder 5 / 16)
    - Rathbun's Business College (Omaha Business College) brochure, 1890 (Box-folder 5 / 17)
    - Miscellaneous, 1890, 1894, undated (Box-folder 5 / 18)
    - List of artifacts transferred to Museum (Box-folder 5 / 19)
- Harriet Shober Nolan
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - Henry Ashton, 1877-1880 (Box-folder 5 / 20)
    - Katherine Corboy (principal of Porthero Indiana Normal School), 1887-1891 (Box-folder 5 / 21)
    - Harry B. Corey, 1888-1892 (Box-folder 5 / 22)
    - Cornelius B. Nolan, 1892-1894 (Box-folder 6 / 1)
    - Frederick S. Rowe, 1884-1892 (Box-folder 6 / 2)
    - Emma Shober Ruhman, 1885-1888 (Box-folder 6 / 3)
    - John H. Shober, Jr., 1885-1899, 1923 (Box-folder 6 / 4)
    - Mary Shober, 1878, 1888-1889 (Box-folder 6 / 5)
    - Nerva Shober, 1879-1893 (Box-folder 6 / 6)
    - T.E. Turner, 1885-1886 (Box-folder 6 / 7)
    - A-V (correspondents include Adair County, Iowa, Schools, Jane B. Angus, Belle C. Carson [in shorthand], J. M. Davidson, E. T. Haughey, Eva Kister, Donnie Linn, Maria Mason, E. J. Rowe, M. B. Smith, G. C. Smith, P. Smith, Mrs. J. A. Snyder, Mrs. Stohl, Jennie Valentine, Joe Valentine, unidentified), 1876-1886 (Box-folder 6 / 8)
    - A-V (correspondents include M. Alderman, B. Black, Mellie Evans, Minnie A. Fountaine, W. L. Hay, C. H. Lamar, W. E. Lindsey, Olive McKee, E. J. Rowe, Mary Shober, G. B. Smith, George F. Stewart, Mrs. W. J. Van Orman, unidentified), 1887 (Box-folder 6 / 9)
    - C-V (correspondents include Lillian A. Cox, William A. Davis, Reba Kerr, Olive McKee, N. V. Smith, Fred Van Orman, unidentified), 1888-1894 (Box-folder 6 / 10)
    - F-S (correspondents include Frank M. Fitzgerald, William Scallon, Genevieve Walsh), 1922-1929 (Box-folder 6 / 11)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - to Mary Shober; John H. Shober, Jr.; miscellaneous, 1887, 1901 (Box-folder 6 / 12)
  - Financial Records
    - Financial statements, 1928-1929 (Box-folder 6 / 13)
  - Miscellany
    - Household inventory; teaching certificates; etc., 1876-1885, 1926 (Box-folder 6 / 14)